Did you ever wonder if certain foods
have a direct effect on your health?
Well, I’m here to
solve that mystery
since you are
the foods you eat.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
We know it’s possible to
cut down our salt intake.
So, what are three practical
steps we can take?
The two most prominent
dietary risks
for death and disability
in the world
are not eating enough fruit
and eating too much salt.
Too little fruit kills nearly
five million people every year,
and too much salt
kills four million.
There are three things
we can do
to lower our
salt intake.
First, don’t add salt
at the table.
A third of us add
salt to our food
before even tasting it!
Number two: Stop adding
salt when cooking.
At first the food
will taste bland.
Two to four weeks later, however,
as the sensitivity of
the salt taste receptors
in the mouth become
more sensitive
to the taste of salt in
the usual concentrations.
Believe it or not
but after two weeks,
you may actually
prefer the taste
of food with less salt.
Some of the flavorings you can use instead
in the meanwhile instead of salt
include using more pepper,
onion, garlic, tomato,
sweet peppers, basil, parsley,
thyme, celery, lime, chilli,
nettle, rosemary, smoke flavor,
curry, coriander, and lemon.
Even if you did add salt, though,
it’s probably better
than eating out,
where even at non-fast
food restaurants,
they tend to
pile it on.
And finally, avoid processed
foods that have salt added.
In most countries only
about half of sodium intake
comes from processed foods,
so there’s more personal
responsibility,
but in the U.S.,
even if we completely
stopped adding salt
in the kitchen and
dining room,
it would only bring down salt
intake a small fraction.
This has led public
health commentators
to note how challenging
it is then for everyone
to reduce their
salt intake
since so much of our sodium intake
is out of our control.
But is it?
We don’t have to buy all
those processed foods.
We can choose not to turn
over our family’s health
to food corporations
that may not have
our best interests
at heart.
If we do buy processed foods
there are two tricks we can use
try to only buy foods
with fewer miligrams of sodium
on the label than there
are grams in the serving size.
So if it’s a 100 gram
serving size,
it should have less than
100mg of sodium.
Or, you can shoot for
fewer milligrams of sodium
than there are calories.
For example here the
sodium is 720;
calories are 260.
720 is greater than 260,
so this has too much sodium.
That’s a trick I learned
from one of my favorite
dieticians of all time,
Jeff Novick.
The reason it works is
because most people get
about 2,200 calories a day,
so if everything you ate
had more calories than sodium
you’d at least get under
2,300 milligrams of sodium
upper limit for healthy
people under age 50.
Of course, the healthiest foods
have no labels at all.
We should also try to buy as
much fresh food as possible,
as it is almost impossible
to come up with a diet
consisting of unprocessed
natural foodstuffs
that exceeds the strict
American Heart Association guidelines
for sodium reduction.
In our next story,
we look at the ways in which salt
may drive autoimmune diseases
such as multiple
sclerosis, psoriasis,
type 1 diabetes,
Sjögren’s syndrome,
asthma, and
rheumatoid arthritis.
Millions suffer from asthma
attacks triggered by exercise.
Within 5 minutes of
starting exercising,
people can get short of breath,
start coughing and wheezing,
such that lung function
significantly drops.
But, on a high-salt diet,
the attack is even worse;
whereas, on a
low-salt diet,
there’s hardly a significant
drop in function at all.
To figure out why, researchers
had them all cough up
sputum from their lungs,
and those on the high-salt diet
ended up with triple
the inflammatory cells
and up to double the concentration
of inflammatory mediators.
But why?
What does salt intake have
to do with inflammation?
We didn’t know...
until now.
The “Western diet,” high in
saturated fat and salt,
has long been postulated
as one potential cause
for the increasing incidence
of autoimmune diseases
in developed countries.
The rapidly increasing incidence
of autoimmune diseases
may be due to an over-
activation of immune cells
called helper 17 cells.
The development of multiple sclerosis,
psoriasis, type I diabetes,
Sjögren’s syndrome, asthma,
and rheumatoid arthritis
has all been shown to involve
this Th17-driven inflammation,
and one trigger for the
activation of those Th17 cells
may be elevated levels of
salt in our bloodstream.
The sodium content of processed
foods and ‘fast food’
can be more than
100 times higher
in comparison to
similar homemade meals.
And, sodium chloride, salt, appears
to drive autoimmune disease
by the induction of these
disease-causing Th17 cells.
Turns out, there’s a salt-
sensing enzyme responsible
for triggering the formation
of these Th17 cells.
Organ damage caused
by high-salt diets
may also activate another type
of inflammatory immune cell.
A high-salt diet can
overwork the kidneys,
starving them of oxygen,
triggering inflammation.
The more salt they
gave people,
the more activation of
inflammatory monocyte cells,
associated with high-salt intake
induced kidney oxygen deficiency,
but this study only
lasted two weeks.
What about long term?
One of the difficulties in
doing sodium experiments
is that it’s hard to
get free-living folks
to maintain a
specific salt intake.
You can do what are called
metabolic ward studies,
where you essentially lock
people in a hospital ward
for a few days and control
their food intake,
but you can’t do that
long term, unless...
you can lock people
in a space capsule.
Mars520 was a 520-day
space flight simulation
to see how people might do
on the way to Mars and back.
What they found was that
those on a high-salt diet
displayed a markedly higher
number of monocytes,
which are a type of immune
cell you often see increased
in settings of chronic inflammation
and autoimmune disorders.
This may reveal one
of the consequences
of excess salt consumption
in our everyday lives,
since that so-called high-salt
intake may actually
just be the average
salt intake.
Furthermore, there was
an increase in the levels
of pro-inflammatory mediators
and a decrease in the level of
anti-inflammatory mediators,
suggesting that high-salt diets
have a potential to bring about
an excessive immune response,
which may damage the immune balance
and result in either
difficulties
in getting rid of
inflammation or
even an increased risk
of autoimmune disease.
What if you already have
an autoimmune disease?
Sodium intake is associated with
increased disease activity
in multiple sclerosis.
If you follow MS
patients for a few years,
those eating more salt
had 3 to 4 times the
exacerbation rate;
three times more
likely to develop
new MS lesions
in their brains,
and on average, had 8
more brain lesions,
14 in their brain
compared to
6 in the low-salt group.
So, the next step is
to try treating patients
with salt reduction and
see if they get better.
But since reducing
our salt intake
is a healthy thing
to do anyway,
I don’t see why anyone
should have to wait.
Did you know that salt can impair
artery function within 30 minutes
by suppressing a key
antioxidant enzyme in our body?
Here’s the story.
If you put people
on a low salt diet,
meaning only getting twice as
much sodium as they need,
as opposed to a
usual salt diet
where they’re getting
five times more,
you get a significant
improvement
in artery function.
Lower salt,
better arterial function;
suggesting heart
protective effects
beyond just blood
pressure reduction.
Now this was after dropping
people’s salt intake
by about a teaspoon
a day for two weeks.
What if you only
dropped salt intake
by like a half
teaspoon a day?
You still get a significant improvement
in artery function,
and it happens within
just two days
of reducing one’s
salt intake.
Or even after
a single meal.
A high salt meal,
which is to say
just a typical amount
of salt consumed
in a commonly
eaten meal,
can significantly suppress
artery function
within 30 minutes.
Now is this in addition
to the spike
in blood pressure
from salt
or because of the spike
in blood pressure?
If you take people with
normal blood pressure
and give them a
bowl of soup
containing how much salt
a regular meal might contain,
their blood pressure
goes up
over the next
three hours
compared to the
same soup
with no added salt.
Now this doesn’t happen
to everyone;
this is just the
average response.
Some people are resistant
to the effects
of salt on their
blood pressure.
So, what if
you repeated
the artery function
experiment on them?
Even in people
whose blood pressure is
unresponsive to salt intake,
they still suffer
significant suppression
of their artery
function.
So even independent of
any effects on blood pressure,
salt hurts our arteries
and that harm begins
within minutes
of it going into
our mouth
for our major
arteries
and even our itty
bitty blood vessels.
Using something called
laser Doppler flowmetry,
you can measure
blood flow
in the tiny vessels
in our skin.
Now to get the blood
vessels to open up
they warmed
up the skin.
The reason we
may turn pink
when we get into
a hot bath
is that the blood vessels in
our skin are opening up.
And that’s
what happens.
Big increase in blood flow
with the warming.
But that’s on the
low salt diet.
A high salt diet,
starts out the same
at the beginning,
but after the
same heating,
there’s significantly
less blood flow.
The arteries just don't
seem to open up as well
on a high salt diet,
unless...
you inject vitamin C
into their skin.
That seems to reverse
the salt-induced
suppression of blood
vessel function.
So if an antioxidant
reverses the salt effect,
then the way salt may be
damaging our artery function
is through
oxidative stress,
the formation of free radicals
in our blood stream.
But how?
There’s an enzyme
in our body
that can detoxify a million
free radicals per second,
24 hours a day,
7 days a week.
But compared to
a low salt diet,
if we consume a
normal salt diet,
we suppress the
activity of this
detoxifying powerhouse
of an enzyme.
That may be
help explain why
with our antioxidant enzymes
crippled by the salt
all the excess
free radicals
may be crippling
our arteries.
But mop up those extra
free radicals up
by infusing vitamin C
into the bloodstream,
and artery function
returns to normal.
Whereas on a
low salt diet,
if you drip vitamin C
into people’s veins,
nothing happens,
because our antioxidant
enzymes
are already taking care
of business
and haven’t been shackled
by the sodium
of a normal-salt diet.
Whereas potassium,
concentrated in fruits
and vegetables,
soften the cells
that line our arteries
and increase the
release of nitric oxide
that allows our
arteries to relax,
sodium in our blood
stiffens the cells
lining our arteries
within minutes,
and reduces nitric
oxide release.
The more salt, the less
nitric oxide is produced.
One salty meal, and not only
does our blood pressure go up
but our arteries
literally stiffen.
That’s why we
could figure out
that too much salt
was bad for us
4,000 years ago.
We don’t need a
double blind trial,
maybe we don’t need to follow
people out for a decade.
You may just have
to feed someone
a bag of potato chips
and take their pulse.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.